um I have to make this video I've made
videos about this before but how do you
manage your time people I have failed so
much in my life to manage my time
properly and I want to tell you some of
the lessons I've learned and this is
we're coming up to the end of the year
and going into a new year and I
hopefully this is a time for us to sort
of you know when I was a Mormon we used
to say repent and recommit right that's
what it is and you know how do you
divide your time up how do you gain
balance and all that stuff but more
importantly what should you spend time
on and i' I've done another video about
this based on the Mormons there's a
thing called good better best and uh I'm
actually going to cite that into
evidence um so it's a it's a talk from
dalan H Oaks uh a big Mormon dude and uh
he talks about good better best and you
know I've always said that it doesn't
matter who the messenger is if if the
true message can come in many different
ways and so you know whether it came
from a a Mormon or not it doesn't matter
the concept is
the concept is this at any moment of
during your day you should ask yourself
what am I doing right now is there
something better I could be doing with
my time am I doing the absolute best
thing I could do with my time I'm not
saying don't play games and don't hang
out with your honey and watch movies and
my wife and I you know we were up until
3:30 in the morning last night we
watched movies we drank beer we had
cheese plates we pet the dog we went for
a walk we just snuggled on the couch for
a good two and a half hours and and then
you know then other stuff um and it was
glorious but you know I I you know I I
burned like five and a half hours is
that a good use of time yeah it is to me
it is because I have the best
relationship I've ever had with my wife
right now and you have to decide where
you're going to invest that time so so
why where is all this coming from
because today you know some completely
innocent person asked me what do you
think of the language of the V language
and I get a little frustrated when
people ask me about completely you know
trendy niche new things and that's you
have to have that they rightly said that
you know you have to have these you know
Nim and and all these other Rusty and
stuff um you know they did try to put go
in the trending category which it isn't
go was always made to create a to solve
a problem and create efficiencies from
the beginning by the creator of Unix and
unicode so that was never a trend uh it
might be trending on the internet but
that's that nothing to do with it as a
technology the point is when you are
presented with the problem
of where do I put my time then you have
to make a decision and you know you can
call it mental mind share you can call
whatever you want um you you really have
to decide where am I going to put my
mental
energy and there are lots of ways to do
this um I actually suggest this is a new
technique I just learned I've been using
it with myself and I make a whole video
on it but I have been scripting my life
scripting myself and what that means is
I've been writing B code that covers
what I want to do and how I want to add
it and um so when you do that you can
decide okay what's the next thing on my
flowchart on my path right and so this
by the way that whole technique will go
into the book autodidactic which I'm
writing which talks about how to manage
your mental energy your mental Capital
where do you put it and so when somebody
I do get a little frustrated when people
whether it's intentional or otherwise
they ask about you know these esoteric
languages and stuff and then you know
sometimes they get a little mean about
it they like to start to troll me and
I'm an easy person to troll and they'll
say things like well why aren't you
screwing around with this or that you
know you're you call him to be a
technologist he's like evaluating new
things and I do but I also it's like a
balancing act because like how much time
do you spend chasing down you know this
thing and is it going to be worth it to
you in the end and um and so let me let
me talk about for me why
I have such a hard time with
particularly edgy things and so maybe
they'll give them like an hour on a
Friday to just look at it and give it a
good look and I I did that once upon a
time with Nim and I really liked it
actually uh once upon a time I did it
with sing SE Lang versus you know the G
SE compiler and I absolutely hate it so
you know keeping up on those things is a
part of the tech lifestyle so let's talk
about that what does it mean to be a
technologist if you're a technologist if
you choose the tech life you are
choosing to keep current on everything
that comes
out that pertains to your job and so
right now what it pertains to my job is
is Believe It or Not Pearl I'm going to
be coding I'm going to be reporting
thousands of L of pearl I'm I've got the
the biggest video on all of YouTube
about Pearl still is and I'm going to
make another big video or two about
Pearl on the command line which is still
the single most powerful command line
tool you can ever use why is Pearl
relevant to me more than V or n or any
of these other things because number one
it's the world's best regx command line
parser blows o away number two I have a
bunch of code for my job that I have to
Port from Pearl to something else and
that language for you might be cobal or
whatever or
Java right so it while it is fun to to
entertain you know looking at new
technologies and stuff like that it it's
not a primary concern if your you know
if your time frame is limited and let's
talk about that again so back to the
commitment to Tech life if you commit so
I'm going to itemize some things here
and I apologize if I offend anybody but
if you commit to a tech life uh you have
to also decide have you committed to a
family are you are you married do you
have children do you have a dog do you
have uh do you desire to maintain some
level of Fitness that keeps you alive
until you're over 50 um these are all
things that substantially impact your
decision about what you do and how does
what does this have to do with with with
learning rust or Nim or something a lot
because because if you're like me as
soon as you start down a trendy path I
have a really hard time pulling myself
away from it you know and and I am you
know I've been starting to ride my bike
again the last couple days and I I went
for like three months without even
getting on my bike why because I was so
focused in my extracurricular activity
of writing Bonsai and writing these
books which I am internally really
motivated to do um so much so that you
know in the my family has paid for it
right because I haven't been there for
whoever at whatever time because I was
so obsessed I remember I remember
staying up till 4:00 a.m. to learn Java
server pages in
1996 and I had young children and I I
was completely exhausted and I felt like
it was an absolute mandatory thing that
I needed to learn it turned that it did
help me it helped me get a job and
helped me get hired and double my income
for learning Java someplace else the
point is is it wasn't secondary it was
the primary thing because it was going
to get me into another job so the reason
that I in that time I learned Java was
because I knew it was related to my
other goals which were to maintain a
family and all this stuff so so the the
takeaway from this
is um you know if if you're
extracurricular activity so so how many
hours do you have in in the in the week
right let's actually do this let's do
this let's do this okay let's say you
know there's there's I mean if you're
working an honest 40 hour week and you
know according to science most people
only work four hour actual work about
four hours a day go look it up I'm not
saying that's just how humans are and so
if you end up working only four hours a
day you know okay maybe you've got that
other time to do the learning some
people would say um this is one of the
reason I think it's so you're so
important to commit to a a job where you
have the time built in it's built in to
what you're getting paid for to do the
learning because then you're getting
paid to learn right so maybe maybe
you're only Co coding um maybe you've
only been coding for for 4 hours or so
but the other 4 hours you've been like
studying the problem and and hopefully
not in a lot of meetings but you know
you've been doing things so how much of
your mental space is dedicated to work
per day you know between 6 to 8 to 10
maybe another day you do 14 hours so
that's up to you but let's let's say
let's just assume that you're working
you know even 30 hours a week okay I
mean 40 40 for most people in the tech
40 hours a week for most people in Tech
is low a lot of tech tech jobs want you
to commit way way way more than six than
40 hours usually about 60 to 80 hours
and you have to decide if that's what
you want for your life because if you
first of all if you choose that and you
choose to have a family I'm telling you
I'm telling you I had to quit Nike
because they were pushing this 90 hours
a week and I my my wife freaked out my
ex-wife she came in and she she went off
on everybody in the room when they told
me on Sunday I had to stay in and is a
whole story but the point of it is is
you need to pick those those choices
right now and decide how much time you
want to spend to each thing and now is a
really good time to start doing the time
budgeting um uh you know um if if you
have toddlers um you know I mean and
maybe maybe you have to do things like
I'm gonna I'm going to mention him but
the primagen right so you know whether
or not I like everything he does doesn't
matter the dude quit his job after
making a lot of money um and is now a
full-time streamer and it's you know
it's impacting his decisions about what
he put's in his stream or something but
he also has young kids and he seems to
be more or less uh attentive to their
needs and stuff to his wife's needs but
he had to quit his job to do that right
so um you know and I've decided to not
quit my job I've decided to have a job
so that I can stream and spend my free
time doing things that I want to do and
not the things that my stream wants me
to do uh that my community wants me to
do and so if you make a decision like
that then you have to fight with the
frustration that I fight with all the
time about not having time to do
everything you want to do because if
you're working in honest 40 hours and
what do how much time do you have a day
let's say you just work out let's say
you just work out for 30 minutes a day
which is the absolute minimum I mean
we're talking about maintaining your
cardio and you're eating right and
everything 30 let's let's make it an
hour because you had to have an extra
shower that day okay so so you know do
the math like 40 plus another five five
5 to 7 hours okay so 47 hours or so and
you you add up the how much time yeah I
actually have a z cast about here when I
did all this I probably should pull it
up but you know the bottom line is that
you are not going to have a lot of extra
time to experiment uh with new things
and so you I think it's more important
that you decide what is the thing that
you need to experiment with that's the
most important thing and it might not be
the sexiest thing so do you know you
know people ask me do I know V I'm like
yeah do you know all of bash do you know
what parameter expansion in bash is no
they don't know do you know how to
background a process in bash no do you
know how to do you know a go command
line tool do you know how to you know
make a manage do you know how to do
these things and most of the people that
are screwing around with with rust or or
n or V or these kind of things they they
don't even know they have no idea and
yet they are technologist employed you
know using a Unix like system every day
and they don't know how to use the
system and and I'm not being mean here
I'm just telling you and they're like
yeah but I don't want to do that you
know it's like I have to do that it's
not the thing I want to do that's a a
quote from Russ anaman and Sil belly
Richard Richard I don't want you to do
the thing you need to do I want what do
you want what do you want to do he wants
to make a new internet is what he wants
to do which I did try to do as well so
the bottom line is we need
to um
establish what those things are that we
should be and this go this goes to the
whole conversation I used to have with a
skill stack um yeah so now I mean the
good news is you're never going to learn
at all right there's always going to be
more to learn um but you know ask
yourself is it more important that I
learn how to use anible or or you know
Cloud that and terraform or something
then that I I learn Nim and whatever now
to be fair I'm going to end on this okay
a lot of people all the people that are
doing Advent of whatever right now I
mean I consider it a waste of time I
consider it a total total waste of time
and that is a very unpopular opinion
like what are you doing why are you
hating I'm not I'm just telling you I
don't want to do it here's why because I
would be rather making a video
complaining about
it but more importantly I I would I
would rather be I would rather be just
you know learning what I need to learn
or working on the things that I need to
work on and but that's not fun right the
reason people do Advent is because they
say it's fun it's actually not go watch
the people doing it they are not having
fun it is hard work and like it'll be
rewarding when I get it done yeah but so
with like any number of thing the the
point is is that we still should be
doing things that are fun and for a lot
of people say Hey you know I work on
coding in my free time because that's
what I like to do in my free time like
that's fine but how much free time do
you really have seriously how much free
time per day do you have I work at home
so I don't have a 2hour commu or
whatever and if I were to work out for
an hour and I was working an 8 hour day
and I was to spend three hours with my
family 8 let's do it 8 9 10
12 13 or so so you know let's say get an
hour for taking care of things and maybe
an hour for for you know cleaning
garbage of and stuff you you might have
maybe two hours a day maybe two hours a
day to spend on your your fun stuff
right now as for me I I bike for 90
minutes a day so that burns most in fact
when I was doing a lot of biking I
wasn't doing any technology because I
didn't have enough time for both I I
literally didn't if if you want to train
to be a triathlete or anything and
you're doing like three hours a day of
endurance training uh 90 minutes a day
plus you know maybe some more counts
like that there's just no way to balance
it it's like you have to pick one and
and I have picked one and I just blimped
out like a balloon over the last three
months um if you're okay but see that's
that's fair somebody mentioned in the
chat well what about single people
single people probably have about eight
hours a day of single of free time
that's probably true in fact I would I
would say that that's probably true um
it was it hasn't been that hasn't been
true for me for a very long time now I
don't have the kids time but but back
when I had young kids I spent at least
two hours a day with the kids at least
at least two hours kids and I'm so happy
I did that because because the life
events kept took the kids from me later
had I not done that I would not have
that time to to look back on and to
remember and you know so let's so on an
average day I would spend you know like
two hours or so with the kids and I
would spend maybe an hour or two with my
wife you know after the kids went to bed
it was really really cherished time
sometimes we would not do that sometimes
I would go play at the time world of war
craft and you know she would go watch
some stupid TV show and sometimes we but
you know we were always split guilty
because we weren't together during that
time and because some of the stuff she
watch I'm like
no Desperate Housewives really no I
don't want to watch that anyway so you
know it's like do you split and do your
own thing or do you think do things
together and I'm very very happy to say
that that uh yeah wow was so popular
it's it's funny to say I mean everybody
knows wow knows it's a huge dedication
of
time yeah yeah I know everybody's
getting really popular in wow yeah yeah
I I saw a lot of people playing it so
but you know grinding in wow is you you
cannot sit down and play like a 40
minute game of wow you're sitting down
and you're playing like a three- hour
game of wow and the point is is quite
simple you there's not a lot of time
left over there's no you know unless
you're single I mean if you're single
and you have nothing else you have no
other social at all then then fine and
and quite honestly I think that
describes a lot of of twitch streamers
and and I'm not trying to pick pick pick
a fight here but if you look hey Chris
if you look at twitch and even YouTube
for that matter the the people who have
for some reason the people who seem to
have the most time to make content also
don't have like families and and I that
is so that's going to be taken wrong I
don't mean it to I'm just trying to tell
you what's realistic right so if you
have a family and you want to get a
better job in
Tech and you also want to play WoW or
whatever you're going to have very very
little time
left uh to learn anything trendy you
know what I me mean yeah people have
their own chat families in fact it's
become I used to yell at people for
using the term fam in my chat I don't
anymore but you know because it's just
slang but it it you know it's where we
are and if and if I was a young person
today I would not have kids so I I got
no problem admitting that I
think there's just no way there's no way
I love my children but there's no way I
would have kids in the current
environment and that's a totally
different topic which we're not going to
go down so so if you're going to
Trend you know and you're going to play
around with the trends or you're going
to watch the videos that are more about
drama between streamers and things like
that that's your choice but but but I
don't have that kind of time you know I
I got a lot of things I want to do I
want to accomplish even though my kids
are are grown and in college and more or
less okay um you know I I still want to
spend time maintaining this amazing
relationship with my wife and I want to
get healthy again and and so I only
learn the languages that I need for work
and and or that I might need in the
future and I spent a little bit of extra
time when I spend time playing around
with stuff at home I'm going to work on
my my uh proxmox you know home H blab
Tower which I am going to start doing
again and I'm building out you know
technology at home that's entertaining
but also helps me work harder uh and you
know be a be a better person work am I
am I like Pro capitalist um you know
that's not really the reason I'm saying
all these things I'm I'm I'm just I'm
just old and and I got things I want to
accomplish so so I I ain't got no time
to like go look at some you know trendy
word thing maybe like 15 minutes right
that I also don't play games anymore
right so I haven't I love DOTA and I
love OverWatch and stuff I haven't even
played uh any of those games um for God
at this point going on two years now so
you know I um you know I don't want
people to misunderstand it walk away and
say Rob is saying that everybody should
be good little automatons working for
corporate America and you shouldn't
spend any time doing anything that would
prevent you from being the highest
performing you know know corporate uh
drone that's not what I'm saying what
I'm saying is to have a balanced life
you don't have as much uh time to play I
love deadlock too I've heard about it
but it yeah there's a lot of great games
and and quite honestly I sort of Envy
some of the people who have time to play
games uh actually can be kind kind of
become a grumpy person because you know
how it is where you like project out
your values on other people depending on
what's most important to you in the
moment it's like a human thing um and so
when you like when I have a lot of
things that I want to do that I feel
like could change the world in a way
that I want before I leave the world um
I start to get Aaron Schwarz about the
whole thing it's like why are you not
spending every free second of your time
doing this and then I get kind of
annoyed by people who are not sharing my
values and then they become kind of a
dick because then I'm like wagging my
finger at people it's like why are you
not a vegetarian like me and you know
what I mean or like why are you not
committed to saving the world like me
I'm busting my ass to save the world and
you're [__] playing World of Warcraft
that game's been dead for 10 10 years or
whatever you know so
I it's just human nature to do that it's
human nature it it's a natural thing
yeah you think it's a natural
narcissistic thing I don't know if I
would say that because I know lot of
people who do that they're not
narcissists um so and and I probably am
a narcissist as well but I'm just saying
that it's like it's a thing anyway
that's been a long video I'm going to
put the the stop button it's sayy it's
20 minutes I thought it would be under
that the the point of it is this is why
you know figure out what you want to
work on and then make a goal and then
make a write a flowchart maybe script to
the flowchart so you can see what your
you know where your flow is your logic
flow WR code right actual code right
bash code which we're now going to do by
the way and and then you can um you know
you can you can organize your own what
you're going to do and I I have done
that for myself so um so so so that's
what I'm doing um anyway